All right, let's begin. Today we are in the second
פרק *Perek* of מסכת סנהדרין *Masechet Sanhedrin*. We are on דף יט
*Daf Yud Tet*. We will be starting from דף יט עמוד ב
*Daf Yud Tet Amud Bet*, three lines down, starting with the word
קפסיק ותני *Kapasik Vetani*. Our משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, the פרק *Perek* is
basically talking about special laws
as far as the קדושה *Kedusha* and various laws concerning the dignity
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* and the מלך melech
*Melech* are concerned. And the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* said that when it
comes to the king, sorry, when it comes to the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, that we do not do, that the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* does not do חליצה *Chalitza*.
That's what it said in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קפסיק ותני *Kapasik Vetani*. This rule
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* does not do, does
not do, sorry, does not do יבום *Yibbum*. If you look actually,
if you just take a look at the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna*, the
משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* said: כהן גדול Kohen Gadol דן ודנין אותו מעיד
ומעידין אותו חולץ וחולצין לאשתו ומיבמין את אשתו *Kohen Gadol dan vedannin
oto meid umeidatoto choletz vecholtzin le-ishto umeyabmin et ishto*.
So when it comes to יבום *Yibbum*, if the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol. *Kohen Gadol* passes,
we do do יבום *Yibbum* to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol*'s wife if they did not have children. אבל avel הוא אינו
מייבם *Aval hu eino meyabbem*, but the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol* himself
does
not do יבום *Yibbum* if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*
brother passes, מפני שהוא אסור באלמנה *Mipnei shehu asur be-almanah*. Right? One
of the prohibitions for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* is
to marry an אלמנה *almanah*. And once his brother passes, his sister-in-law
is an אלמנה *almanah*, and therefore he cannot, he cannot perform the
מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *Yibbum*. So on that law of the משנה
mishna *Mishna*, if you go back to the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, our
starting point גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on יח עמוד ב *Yud Cheit Amud
Bet* on the bottom, the last three words, the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* said that the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* stated quite categorically
that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* can never do יבום
*Yibbum*.
Now, just as an introduction, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* can
never do יבום *Yibbum*.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* has two, two laws concerning
his personal status. One is that he cannot marry an אלמנה *almanah*,
he cannot marry a woman who's been married before. And there's another
prohibition that sort of stated as a, as an עשה *Aseh*, and
that's
not a widow or or a divorcee or both? A widow. I
know but you just said someone that was never married.
Oh, well,
right.
Sorry.
All כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* cannot marry a...
all כהנים *Kohanim* cannot marry a divorcee. He also cannot marry an
אלמנה *almanah*. Thank you. Appreciate that.
On top of that, it says in the Torah: בתולה יקח *Betulah
yikach*, he has to marry a בתולה *betulah*.
So, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קפסיק ותני *Kapasik Vetani*. The
משנה mishna *Mishna* stated categorically: לא שנא מן האירוסין ולא שנא מן
הנישואין *Lo shna min ha-erusin velo shna min ha-nisu'in*. If his brother
passes, we do not distinguish whether the marriage, what stage of marriage
his brother was in. You have the first stage of marriage of
אירוסין *Erusin*, which is the same thing as קידושין *Kiddushin*, where they
initiated the marriage, but they did not consummate the marriage yet.
And then you have the case, then you have the stage of
marriage of נישואין *Nisu'in* where the marriage is eventually consummated and they're
fully-fledged husband and wife.
So the משנה mishnah *Mishna* did not make a distinction when it
came to the law of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*.
בשלמא מן הנישואין הוי עשה ולא תעשה *Bishlama min ha-nisu'in
havi aseh velo ta'aseh*. It
is understandable to say that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*
cannot marry a, cannot do יבום *Yibbum* if his sister-in-law and brother
were already fully married. Why? Because then we have an עשה *aseh*,
that's the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *Yibbum*, ולא תעשה *velo ta'aseh*, and
that's
the prohibition of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* not marrying
an אלמנה *almanah*. ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה *Ve-ein aseh docheh
lo ta'aseh va-aseh*. And we have a, we have a general principle
that when you have a מצות עשה *mitzvat aseh*...
And
a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*, that does not trump a simple עשה
*aseh*. So the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* has an עשה
*aseh* of marrying a בתולה *besulah*, a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh* of
marrying an אלמנה *almanah*, and on the other side he is also
being pushed in the other direction to marry her because of the
מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum*. But here you have two against one,
and the מצות עשה *mitzvas aseh* and לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh* will
not be trumped by the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum*. ואין עשה
דוחה לא תעשה ועשה *V'ein aseh docheh lo ta'aseh v'aseh*. However, one
of these factors gets taken away if we go to the first
page of marriage, אירוסין *eirusin*, where we presume that the woman is
a בתולה *besulah*. We presume that the woman has never, does not
have relations with her husband.
There, if you take away the fact that she's a בתולה *besulah*,
what are we left with? We're left with an עשה *aseh* of
יבום *yibum* and a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh* of אלמנה לא יקח
*almanah lo yikach*. אלא מן האירוסין אמאי אמאי יבא עשה וידחה לא
תעשה *Ella min haeirusin, amai amai? Yavo aseh v'yidcheh lo ta'aseh*.
So why was the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* categorical when it said that
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* could not marry a יבום
*yibum*? It should have made the distinction between קידושין *kiddushin* and נישואין
*nisuin*. In קידושין *kiddushin* there's an עשה *aseh* that is דוחה *docheh*
לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*.
Is that a general rule, an עשה *aseh* always goes over a
לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*?
Yeah. Really? Yeah, that's a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* I think in יבמות
*Yevamos* that they're quoting here in the side, that they derived that
from פסוקים pesukim. *psukim*.
But a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh* trumps everything.
No, it doesn't.
Well, it's not לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*, sometimes... no, the principle is,
they say it right here,
ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה
*v'ein aseh docheh lo ta'aseh*.
I thought
a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh* is stronger?
It's like
your parents don't like the neighbor, you don't go visit the neighbor
because you're honoring your parents, for example.
Right.
Right, that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said. אלא *Ella*...
all the way to the end.
The rabbis instituted a special
prohibition.
Right, but
that's what's
coming up.
Right,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, גזירה gezeirah ביאה ראשונה bi'ah rishonah,
אטו ביאה שנייה bi'ah shniyah *gzeira biah rishonah atu biah shniyah*. So
here, what we don't have, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* responds and says,
we don't have actually a biblical prohibition of the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol *Kohen Gadol* to do יבום *yibum* with his sister-in-law if
she's from אירוסין
*eirusin*,
but rather we have a גזירה *gzeira*. גזירה ביאה biah. ראשונה אטו
ביאה שנייה *Gzeira biah rishonah atu biah shniyah*.
When it comes to ביאה ראשונה *biah rishonah*, that's the only ביאה
*biah* where there is the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* to take
place. If you look in the פסוקים *psukim* of the תורה Torah
*Torah*, it makes it clear that that's the actual מצוה *mitzvah*. Which
is interesting, because you would have thought that יבום *yibum* the מצוה
*mitzvah* is actually to have the child itself, but that's not the
מצוה *mitzvah*. You could say that's sort of like the purpose of
the מצוה *mitzvah*, but in a טעמי המצוות *ta'amei hamitzvos* sort of
fashion, but it's actually just the first ביאה *biah* is the מצוה
*mitzvah*. So this is not, they're saying, an actual דין דאורייתא *din
d'oraissa*, it's a דין דרבנן *din d'rabbanan*. גזירה ביאה ראשונה *Gzeira biah
rishonah*... the concern is, is that if you allow ביאה ראשונה *biah
rishonah*,
the couple will go and have a second ביאה *biah*, and the
second ביאה *biah* is not a מצוה *mitzvah* for the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, and the second ביאה *biah* is not a
מצוה *mitzvah* for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, and then
the איסורים *issurim* of בתולה יקח *besulah yikach* and אלמנה לא יקח
*almanah lo yikach* come back into play, and then you have a
מצות עשה *mitzvas aseh*, לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*, and a מצות עשה
*mitzvas aseh*, and those two will certainly trump the עשה *aseh* of
יבום *yibum*, and we don't want the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol* to do that. So therefore, the חכמים *Chachamim* made a גזירה
*gzeira*. It wasn't a דין דאורייתא *din d'oraissa* expounded in the משנה
*Mishnah*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami
hachi*, we have a support for this idea where the משנה *Mishnah*
says, אם קדמו ובעלו ביאה ראשונה *im kadmu u'va'alo biah rishonah*, קנה
*kno*. And if indeed the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. went ahead, went
against the
גזירה—well, that's not the language in the ברייתא, Baraita, that's sort of
the point. If he went ahead and did have ביאה ראשונה, קנו,
kanu,
they're considered married, ואסור לקיימן בביאה שנייה, v'assur l'kayman b'bi'ah shniyah, but
so then they apparently have to dissolve the relationship and and we
don't allow a scenario where ביאה שנייה continues to exist. Okay. Alright.
This is sort of a choppy גמרא Gemara where we sort of
very quickly are going to go through the various different different parts
of the משנה. Okay. If
you
go back to in the משנה, we saw that we have a
debate between רב מאיר Rav Meir and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda as
to how the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol deports himself when it comes
to following the funeral procession. What are his what are his restrictions?
רב מאיר Rav Meir said,
מת לו מת, meis lo meis, אינו יוצא אחר המיטה. eino yotzei
achar hamitah.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. is not allowed to follow the processional.
I'm just reading from the משנה. הן נכסין והוא נגלה הן נגלין
והוא נכסה. hen nichsin v'hu nigleh hen niglin v'hu nichseh.
When the funeral processional goes out, he is going to sort of
hide, and when they go out
and when they hide, he goes out. Like the point is is
that they are two separate funeral processionals and he's never going to
have any type of contact with him. ויוצא עמהן עד פתח שער
העיר. v'yotzei imahen ad
pesach shaar ha'ir.
But he does indeed go out with them. He does have a
funeral processional until the outskirts of the city. That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. רב יהודה אומר אינו יוצא מן המקדש. Rav Yehuda omer eino
yotzei min ha-Mikdash. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says that the that he's
not allowed to actually leave the Temple. So we'll get back to
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in a minute in the גמרא. gemara Now
the גמרא gemara wants to understand רב מאיר's Rav Meir position. So
back in our גמרא, gemara
one, two, three, four, about six lines down, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, this is the פסוק pasuk that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda is is basing his הלכה halacha on: ומן המקדש לא
יצא. u-min ha-Mikdash lo yeitzei. Says in the תורה Torah
that in in the laws of אבלות aveilus concerning אבלות aveilus in
פרשת אמור Parshas Emor for the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it says
and from the Temple he shall not exit. לא יצא, lo yeitzei,
what does it mean לא יצא? lo yeitzei? לא יצא עמהן, lo
yeitzei imahen, he's not allowed to be with the mourners,
אבל יוצא הוא אחריהן. aval yotzei hu achareihen. But he is allowed
to follow them as long as he is not exactly with them.
כיצד? keitzad? הן נכסין והוא נגלה הן נגלין והוא נכסה. hen nichsin
v'hu nigleh hen niglin v'hu nichseh. Again, he will he'll
make a move as part of the processional and they have to
sort of hide themselves, reveal themselves as he hides himself, hide themselves
as he reveals himself, meaning he is not allowed to be part
of the processional, but he follows the processional along.
Is this because of טומאה tumah or because of dignity or it's
not appropriate?
So we'll see in in a minute, the גמרא makes it clear,
I think, that there's a concern of that he's not allowed to
be מטמא metamei himself, טמא מת. tamei meis. He's not allowed to
touch anything that is a, you know, a dead a dead body
and make himself טמא tamei in that way. And so there's a
concern that he will be מטמא metamei himself
and that's the need for his own separate processional.
So the גמרא says,
ויוצא עד פתח, v'yotzei ad pesach, quoting the משנה, ויוצא עד פתח
שער העיר. v'yotzei ad pesach shaar ha'ir.
שפיר קאמר רב יהודה. shapir ka'amar Rav Yehuda. In the משנה, רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said, רב יהודה אומר אינו יוצא מן המקדש. Rav
Yehuda omer eino yotzei min ha-Mikdash.
רב מאיר Rav Meir said that he's allowed to go out but
he has to have this sort of special special way of following
yet not following the processional. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda has a different
view. He is not allowed to leave the מקדש. Mikdash. He's not
allowed to leave the Temple at all. And then he quotes a
פסוק. pasuk. משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar מן
המקדש לא יצא. min ha-Mikdash lo yeitzei. It says in the תורה
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol should not leave the
Temple. That's why the גמרא said שפיר קאמר רבי יהודה. shappir ka'amar
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said well because he quotes a
פסוק pasuk and the פסוק pasuk simply said and from the temple
the כהן גדול kohen gadol shall not exit.
The פסוק'ס pasuk's not talking about, I mean it's a general פסוק.
pasuk.
Right, right, I mean
obviously he's not stuck for the rest of his life.
Right. Oh, so that's going to be the response of רב מאיר.
Rav Meir. But the שפיר shappir is on that he's quoting a
פסוק pasuk at least, that
the גמרא generally he's quoting a פסוק pasuk and the other side
is not is a sort of at least straightforward words of the
פסוק, pasuk,
even if the context is off. אמר
לך רב מאיר אי הכי לביתו נמי לא. Amar lach Rav Meir
i hachi levayto nami lo.
If this is true, he shouldn't be able to go from the
מקדש mikdash even into his home.
This is sort of a reductio ad absurdum. If the concern we'll
see later on is that he shouldn't become טמא מת tamei meit
and the sanctuary for him is the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
then not only should the law simply be that he's not allowed
to leave the מקדש mikdash to go to the funeral procession, but
the law is he shouldn't be able to leave the מקדש mikdash
even to go home because there should be a concern
that he'll become טמא מת. tamei meit. But we know for a
fact that he's allowed to leave his home. Therefore that concern is
reduced to an absurd concern.
אלא הכי קאמר. Ela hachi ka'amar. So now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to show, demonstrate how רב מאיר Rav Meir read the
פסוק. pasuk. מן המקדש לא יצא מקדושתו
לא
יצא.
Min hamikdash lo
yetzei
mikedushato lo
yetzei.
He should be careful not to leave his state of holiness meaning
טומאת מת.
tum'at meit.
וכיון דאית ליה הכירא Vekeivan de'is lei hekera
and since he has a הכירא, hekera, meaning he's acting in a
way that clearly separates himself out from the party, the funeral procession,
and once he's clearly acting in a different way and he's separate
from the party, that is enough of a הכירא, hekera, that is
enough of a distinguishing action that he'll be reminded not to be
careful and not become טמא מת. tamei meit. כיון דאית ליה הכירא
לא אתי למינגע. Keivan de'is lei hekera lo ati leminga. He will
not come to touch anything that is dead or anything that is
טמא מת tamei meit
and therefore there is no longer any concern that he will become
טמא מת. tamei meit. And that is how רב מאיר Rav Meir
reads פסוקים. So how does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda take care of
that concern of touching something that is טמא מת? tamei meit? רבי
יהודה אגב מרירא דלמא מקרי ואתי ונגע. Rabbi Yehuda agav merira dilma
mikrei ve'ati venaga.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
that's not, you know, simply walking with the procession in a way
that is separate and distinct is not good enough of a הכירא
hekera because out of grief
a person loses their judgment a little bit and might come to
touch something that is טמא מת tamei meit and that's not considered
sufficient type of הכירא. hekera. Okay.
Now in the next part of our משנה we're talking about the
כהן גדול'ס Kohen Gadol's practices in a בית אבל beit avel
and this ברייתא'ס baraita's going to talk about the physical position of
the כהן גדול. kohen gadol How does, where does he stand and
how does he act
vis-a-vis the rest of the officials that are with him from the
temple to achieve ניחום אבלים nichum avelim and how is ניחום אבלים
nichum avelim done to him? What are sort of the physical ritual,
how does it look like? תנו רבנן כשהוא מנחם. Tanu rabanan keshehu
menachem. תנו רבנן כשהוא עובר בשורה
לנחם את אחרים. Tanu rabanan keshehu
over beshura
lenachem es acherim.
When the כהן גדול kohen gadol. passes the שורה, shura, the line
of mourners that comfort the mourners, סגן ומשוח שעבר בימינו. Sgan umashuach
she'avar biyemino.
So now we're introduced to sort of the
temple's ceremonial crew so to speak that comes from the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash that does ניחום אבלים. nichum avelim. So you have the
כהן גדול kohen gadol then you have the... סגן כהן גדול Sgan
Kohen Gadol is the assistant to the כהן גדול kohen gadol ומשוח
שעבר. umashuach she'avar. משוח שעבר Mashuach she'avar
רש״י Rashi explains is the previous כהן גדול, kohen gadol sort of
like the designated hitter but not quite. He was someone who אירע
בו פסול ira bo pasul and
רש״י Rashi doesn't explain what kind of פסול. pasul. Perhaps he got
ill or his wife passed away. It's not clear. These are just
guesses.
But apparently a כהן גדול kohen gadol can be temporarily taken out
of commission due to some type of a פסול, psul, some sort
of a defect. And it could be temporary but still is considered
on the board
of ceremonial functions for the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So going to do ניחום אבלים, nichum aveilim, you have the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol the סגן, Sgan, and the משוח שעבר Mashuach she'avar
בימינו. biyimino. So to the right of the כהן Kohen גדול you
have these two כהנים, the סגן, Sgan, the assistant, and the משוח
שעבר. Mashuach she'avar. And to the left of the כהן Kohen, גדול
you have the ראש בית אב, Rosh Beis Av, you have the
head of the family that is mourning,
האבלים, ha'aveilim, וכל העם משמאל. vechol ha'am mismol. And then to the
left, further down from the head of the family, you have the
actual mourners and everyone else. Those were all to the left. So
right in the middle of every mourner house of mourning, if the
כהן Kohen גדול was there, the כהן Kohen גדול gets the middle
right next to the house of the family.
So the כהן גדול can't have a מום, mum, right? Right. That
might be one
פסול.
psul. Right, a מום, mum, but something that could repair itself apparently.
Right, we're talking about a כהן at a funeral, not his own,
but somebody else's. Not his own, ניחום. nichum.
But the next right now and now we're about to go on
to
when the כהן גדול is the mourner. The very next line now,
and what happens if the כהן גדול is the mourner? כשהוא עומד
בשורה ומתנחם מאחרים, Keshehu omed beshura umisnachem me'acherim,
and when he is עומד בשורה omed beshura and he is the
mourner and gets comfort from others, סגן מימינו, Sgan miyimino,
to his right is the סגן, Sgan, וראש בית אב, verosh beis
av,
and then comes the head of the family who's mourning, וכל העם
משמאלו. vechol ha'am mismalo.
And then, I'm sorry, to his left is the head of the
family and everyone else who is mourning. Now, if you notice, there
was somebody missing from this list. Previously, we had משוח שעבר, Mashuach
she'avar,
another כהן גדול who is not there because of some sort of
an injury, some sort of a פסול. psul. So when the כהן
גדול is mourning,
this other person
משוח שעבר Mashuach she'avar is not there. So the גמרא notices this
and asks, אבל משוח שעבר לא אתי גביה? Aval Mashuach she'avar lo
asi gabei? Did the משוח שעבר Mashuach she'avar not go and visit
him? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? חלש
דעתיה סבר קחדי בי.
Chalsha dateih savar kachadi bi.
The כהן גדול would be weak from his presence, from the
presence of the משוח שעבר. Mashuach she'avar.
He would think he is happy as a result of me being
in mourning. Now, I'm not sure how to explain this,
whether to think that everyone thinks these
types
of thoughts that seem to be a little bit nasty.
No, but it's the משוח, Mashuach, like he had a פסול psul
and so he can't be כהן, but when the פסול psul goes
away, whatever that was, then he can חוזר לעבודתו. chozer la'avodaso. Oh,
on רש״י Rashi it's... I'm not sure if I understand it correctly.
So then maybe he's happy at the misfortune
of
the other כהן because now he can
assume position, right, right, כהן גדול.
So
he's not like happy just because, whatever, happy something bad happened. He's
just... Schadenfreude. Yeah, he's happy for somebody to...
for the
כהן
גדול to somewhat in the interim... Right,
until the משוח Mashuach comes back, he's just sort of falling in
his place.
Right. Right. So I guess I was just going to say that
this is just
normal human condition.
סגן כהן גדול Sgan Kohen Gadol is
like... Hello, סגן Sgan in modern Hebrew is vice, like vice president.
So this isn't like the same idea that if any trouble happening
that he can replace him?
No, the סגן... Sgan... is more of like an assistant. We'll see
here that the גמרא is about to say that he's like the
ממונה, Mamona,
like the, that's more of the assistant. But the משוח שעבר Mashuach
She'avar
is more of a is more of like an associate,
associate kind of.
Okay. Yeah, thank you. Thank you. חלשא דעתיה סבר כחד בי, Chalsha
dateih savar kechad bei, so because of this, because of this competition
that's there, I think this is like being sensitive, we're going to
say as a rule that the משוח שעבר Mashuach She'avar does not
show up to the to the to the house of mourning of
the כהן גדול.
Okay.
אמר פפא, Amar Pappa, you might think it might be the other
way around, that because they're sharing these responsibilities,
they they develop a friendship, yeah, a connection of of equals in
a way, you know,
they're like past president. But here he can come back, he can
continue like to go in and out, right, the משוח? Mashuach? He
can whenever that happens to the כהן גדול, the משוח Mashuach can
then be the כהן גדול for that day and then that keeps
happening?
I'm not sure of the of the process there.
I don't know if this is relevant but look at the
רש"י Rashi there to משוח שעבר Mashuach She'avar from like seven or
eight or nine lines from the top, it says כגון שאירע בו
פסול בכהן גדול ומינוהו תחתיו וכשעבר פסולו של ראשון חוזר לעבודתו. Kegon
she'ira bo psul b'Kohen Gadol uminuhu tachtav ukeshe'avar psulo shel rishon chozer
l'avodato.
So he's like he was pushed away from his position because he
had a פסול, psul, but when the פסול psul is going to
go away he'll be able to...
Right, but if he has another פסול, psul, does the same individual,
is he the one who comes and keeps filling in? I think
so.
Oh,
okay.
But
it might be that he comes back just because his replacement isn't
available but his פסול psul is still there...
right,
right.
I'm
not sure that he has to wait for the first one for
the replacement to be disqualified before he can come back. Right.
That's not clear from here.
Right, as soon as his פסול... psul... yeah, that's what I...
It's not clear from here what right those laws are not are
not being clarified from here.
Okay. Okay, going on. We are at אמר פפא שמע מינה תלת.
Amar Pappa Shma Mina Tlat. From this משנה we learn three things.
From this תוספתא Tosefta we learn three things. שמע
מינה היינו סגן היינו ממונה,
Shma mina hainu sgan hainu
mamona, that the vice, the assistant כהן is the same thing as
a ממונה. mamona. There's another ברייתא braita where we see that the
word ממונה mamona is used. שמע מינה אבלים עומדים וכל העם עוברים.
Shma mina avelim omdim vechol ha'am ovrim. We see from here that
the procedure is, what's the procedure for ניחום אבלים nichum avelim at
the
at the בית הקברות beit hakevarot is that the who is moving
in that procedure, the אבלים avelim are standing and everyone else does
the passing by the אבלים. avelim. שמע מינה אבלים לשמאל המנחמים הן
עומדים. Shma mina avelim l'smol hamenachamim hen omdim.
And now we see further more specifically in the in the procedure,
the אבלים avelim are to the left of those who are getting
comfort and those who are comforting are standing. All
right, now we get a little bit more history to this notion
of the אבלים avelim where stand and the עם am would pass
would pass by the אבלים. avelim. תנו רבנן בראשונה היו אבלים עומדים
וכל העם עוברים והיו שתי משפחות בירושלים מתגרות זו בזו. Tanu Rabbanan
berishona hayu avelim omdim vechol ha'am ovrim vehayu shtei mishpachot b'Yerushalayim mitgarot
zu b'zu.
So originally
the אבלים avelim would stand to do in the שורה shura of
ניחום אבלים nichum avelim וכל העם עוברים vechol ha'am ovrim
and the rest of the nation would pass by the אבלים, avelim,
but there were two families in Jerusalem that would fight with each
other. זאת אומרת אני עוברת תחילה זאת אומרת אני עוברת תחילה התקינו
שיהא עם עומדים ואבלים עוברים. Zot omeret ani overet techila zot omeret
ani overet techila hitkinu sheyehai am omdim v'avelim ovrim.
So when these two families would try to perform ניחום אבלים nichum
avelim they would fight, who does, who gets the honor
of going first to perform ניחום אבלים, nichum avelim, this one said
I go first, I get to pass by first, this one said
I get to pass by first. So they made a תקנה, takana,
no, העם עומדים, ha'am omdim, no the עם am is going to
stand and the mourners are going to pass by. So even though
it's not ideal when it comes to the actual... procedures of הלכות
אבילות, hilchos aveilus, אבילות, aveilus,
apparently the values here are that in order to prevent this type
of jockeying and this type of concern for כבוד kavod and fighting,
we're going to tweak the laws of אבילות aveilus in order to
show the values of
כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos and and not wanting to have fights taking
place.
So that's what we do instead. It's to do it opposite of
how we do it and now we do it right where the
the mourners pass and everyone stands.
Yeah,
you can keep in mind that that practice has other values of
not wanting of not of the value of peace is
is buried historically into that into that practice. Okay,
we're still going to talk about these mourning practices. אמר רבי בר
אבא החזיר רבי יוסי את הדבר ליושנו בציפורי.
Amar Rabbi Bar Abba hechzir Rabbi
Yosi et hadavar leyoshno betzipori. Rabbi also returned this the
practice of the שורה, shura, who gets to pass whom, to its
original practice in ציפורי. Tzipori. שיהיו אבלים עומדים וכל העם עוברים. Sheyihiyu
aveilim omdim vechol ha'am overin.
He made it that
that the mourners would be the one who pass by and all
the nation
and everyone else that doesn't become אבלים aveilim would would pass. I'm
sorry, all the all the mourners would stand and everyone else would
pass by. אמר רבי בר אבא התקין רבי יוסי בציפורי שלא תהא
אשה מהלכת בשוק ובנה אחריה.
Amar Rabbi Bar Abba hitkin Rabbi Yosi betzipori shelo tehei isha mahalachet
bashuk
uvna achareha.
A woman shouldn't walk in the marketplace
while her child is walking behind her משום מעשה שהיה, mishum ma'aseh
shehayah,
because of something, a story that happened.
Now the גמרא doesn't tell us what the story was that took
place.
If you take a look at רשי, Rashi, it's in the middle
of רשי׳ס, Rashi's, first word is לפניה, lifaneha, but the דיבור המתחיל
dibur hamaschil is משום מעשה שהיה. mishum ma'aseh shehayah.
The people see that רשי? Rashi? שנגנבוהו פריצים מאחריה. Shenignavu-hu pritzim me'achareha.
There were
kidnappers
kidnapped the child from behind her. ונתנוהו בבית Venatnu-hu bebayit
and they put him in a home. וכשחזרה ולא ראתה, Uchshechazra velo
ra'ata,
and when his mother turned around and didn't see her, התחילה צועקת
ובוכה. hitchila tzo'eket uvocheh.
She started to yell and cry. בא אחד מהם ואמר בואי ואראנו.
Ba echad meihem ve'amar bo'i ve'arenu. One of the kidnappers
went and said to her, come I will show you where he
is. הלכה ונכנסה אחריו ועינוה. Halcha venichnesa acharay ve'inutam.
Then they went and one of them went and and raped her.
So
I don't know exactly where רשי Rashi how רשי Rashi knows all
the various parts of the story. The two basic parts are kidnapping
and rape. But this is the second this is the second this
is the second
תקנה takana of רבי יוסי בציפורי Rabbi Yosi betzipori that the child
shouldn't walk so far away from the mother, but they should presumably
they should walk very close to the mother. ואמר רבי בר אבא
התקין רבי יוסי בציפורי שיהיו נשים מספרות בבית הכסא משום ייחוד. Ve'amar
Rabbi Bar Abba hitkin Rabbi Yosi betzipori sheyihiyu nashim mesaprot beveit hakisse
mishum yichud.
He also made a תקנה takana that women out of a concern
for the laws of ייחוד yichud should talk to each other while
they're in the bathroom. So what exactly is the concern and what
does the talking together in the bathroom accomplish? So if you take
a look at רשי, Rashi, זו עם זו, zu im zu,
and then you see the word משום ייחוד. mishum yichud. It's about
about
lines up. משום ייחוד. Mishum yichud. רשי Rashi says: שמא ילך אדם
שם ואם לא ישמע קול אדם יכנס ויתייחד שם.
shema yeilech adam sham ve'im
lo yishma kol adam yikanes veyityached sham.
So let's say you have two women in the bathroom or one
woman in the bathroom, a man will walk in there, he doesn't
know. Who's there? So if one woman is there or two women
are there, at least in the laws of ייחוד, yichud, they make
a distinction between an אדם כשר, adam kasher, sort of a person
who is an upright person.
Even there, there'll be ייחוד yichud with two women
or maybe not with two women. But there'll be ייחוד. yichud. So
what
so how does this help? דתנן... detnan... let me just read down.
לא יתייחד אדם עם שתי נשים. lo yityached adam im shtei nashim.
And it says the משנה that a person should not have ייחוד,
yichud, a man should not have ייחוד yichud with two women. That's
considered ייחוד. yichud. So how so what's the cure for this is
that the two women should talk to each other and the man
will know that they're two women and then there won't be any
longer ייחוד. yichud.
Okay, what's interesting about this is that ordinarily when we think of
ייחוד, yichud, we think that there's like a time associated with it.
Like ייחוד yichud is like six minutes, seven minutes, or five minutes,
something of that nature that that it's not just a situation, you
know, there's two women there and a man and that's ייחוד, yichud,
but there's a certain amount of time that has to elapse in
order for there to be ייחוד. yichud. It's called like זמן ביאה,
zman biah, the amount of time it would take for cohabitation to
take place. According to according to this רש"י, Rashi, you know,
it seems like that the there isn't that time issue because he
never mentions it. You know, if a person has to go to
the bathroom and it's not going to be longer than five minutes,
according to the scenario that רש"י Rashi is setting up, it shouldn't
be a problem. So according to רש"י, Rashi, it seems like it's
possible to say that ייחוד yichud is not an issue of that
time factor is not there. For רש"י Rashi it's simply a scenario.
You have two women and one man in a certain certain type
of setting. That setting itself constitutes ביאה. The יד רמה Yad Ramah
here says that because of that concern against רש"י, Rashi,
I believe, that
that ייחוד yichud is not about a setting but it has other
factors as well. It has to take a certain amount of time.
It has to elapse. He says that actually the women should just
talk out loud
and give an impression that there are a lot of people there.
And if there are a lot of people there, anybody who wants
to come and do any type of harm will not come and
and have ייחוד yichud will do ייחוד. yichud.
Okay.
Is this an anti-rape protection?
So I think for the יד רמה Yad Ramah it sounds like
more of an anti-rape protection type of law, whereas for רש"י Rashi
it seems more of like a halachic ייחוד yichud type of law.
Yeah.
It seems from this רש"י Rashi we've learned that we're talking about
bathrooms that were set up there out out right. So those were
unisex. So so maybe we can infer that in in the cities
they had separate bathrooms. Right. So that's why he's
contemplating that this is like outhouses setting or something like
that.
Okay.
I'm
up to second last of the skinny lines on the page. אמר
רב מנשיא בר שלוב שאילתיה
דרב יוסף מרבי יאשיה רבה בבית עלמין דהוצל.
Amar Rav Menashya bar Shlub she'ilteih deRav Yosef
meRabbi Yoshiya Rabbah bebeit almin deHutzal. I asked רב יאשיה רבה
Rav Yoshiya Rabbah in the in the בית עלמין beit almin in
the cemetery in הוצל. Hutzal. Doesn't say what the questions were. ואמר
לי veamar li אין שורה פחותה מעשרה בני אדם. ein shura p'chuta
measara bnei adam. So the שורה shura has to have ten בני
אדם bnei adam ואין אבלים מן המניין. veein avelim min haminyan. But
the אבלים avelim don't count in the מניין. minyan. Which makes sense.
They're the center of the אבלים avelim are the center of the
ritual. The whole point is to for the community to gather around
them and comfort them. So it makes sense that they don't count
in the מניין minyan here, as opposed to all other times when
it comes to אבילות avilut they certainly count towards the
מניין. minyan. בין שאבלים עומדים וכל העם עוברים בין שאבלים עוברים וכל
העם עומדים. bein she'avelim omdim vechol haam overim bein she'avelim overim vechol
haam omdim. And finally when it comes to the שורה, shura, when
it comes to the ניחום אבלים, nichum avelim, אבלים avelim can stand,
the ceremony can be where the אבלים avelim stand. and the rest
of the community passes by or it can be where the community
stands and the אבלים avelim can pass by. Okay כשהוא מתנחם. k'shehu
mitnachem.
Our משנה talked about what is the formula when the כהן
גדול is in אבילות. avelut.
What exactly is the formula for the כהן גדול the people say
to the כהן גדול. And now the גמרא wants to know what
is the formula that the כהן גדול pronounces. The משנה never said
that. So the גמרא says איבעיא להו ibaya lehu כי מנחם הוא
אחריני היכא אמר להו? ki m'nachem hu achrinei heicha amar lehu? When
he does ניחום אבלים nichum avelim for other people what does he
say? תא שמע ta shema והוא אומר תתנחמו. v'hu omer titnachamu.
היכי
דמי?
heichi
dami? When he says you shall be comforted what is
the case? Meaning is he the comforter? That sounds sort of right
like he's saying you shall be comforted. That's normally when you are
the comforter the one offering comfort that's what you say. היכי דמי?
heichi dami? אילימא כי מנחמי אחריני לדידיה?
ilima ki m'nachamei
achrinei l'didi? Is the situation that others are comforting him and
he
says
תתנחמו titnachamu you shall be comforted? אמר להו אינהו תתנחמו? amar lehu
inhu titnachamu? נחשא קא
רמי להו? nechasha ka rami lehu? Is he like throwing a bad
sign at them? If that's the case?
Right just again we're trying to figure out we know that the
כהן גדול says תתנחמו titnachamu you shall be comforted. We don't know
whether that is part of when he says ניחום אבלים nichum avelim
or not. And now we're saying well let's assume it's
when others do ניחום אבלים. nichum avelim. How does that sound? If
he is actually an אבל avel
excuse me if he is the אבל avel and others are comforting
him and then he says back תתנחמו titnachamu you should be comforted
that sounds like a curse. You know you're the mourner and someone
says to you you should be comforted and you say back you
should be comforted too that sort of sounds like you're saying something
bad should happen to you too. That's תתנחמו titnachamu נחשא קא רמי
להו. nechasha ka rami lehu. אלא כי מנחם לאחריני
ela ki
m'nachem l'achrinei rather it's when the כהן גדול is מנחם m'nachem others
אמר להו amar lehu תתנחמו. titnachamu. It's when he is מנחם אבל
m'nachem avel it's when he is comforting mourners he has the phrase
תתנחמו titnachamu you shall be comforted. שמע מינה. shma mina.
Okay now we're no longer talking about the כהן גדול but we're...
So is that talking in the plural somehow analogous to what we
say now המקום ינחם אתכם? Hamakom yenachem etchem?
Oh that sounds like it. That's interesting.
תתנחמו titnachameinu you shall be comforted in the plural.
Yeah I
didn't notice how that I didn't notice how that
you're supposed to say it even if there's just one אבל and
this sounds like maybe it's the same
thing. Excellent
point. Excellent
point. That the point being made is that the language here of
תתנחמו titnachamu is said in the plural just like the standard formula
used today.
Okay isn't that because there are a number of mourners?
Well it could be because there are a number of mourners but
it could also be just we also do it just for one
mourner
in the plural.
So it's like
a typical לשון רבים lashon rabbim using the
plural.
Okay so we'll stop here today. The
next גמרא will go on to talk about מלך melech and why
there isn't why מלכות ישראל malchut Yisrael does not get to adjudicate.
There is a nice long אגדתא agadata about that.
Also the
feel
like the מלך is supposed to have כבוד kavod right? A sense
of honor. He's not supposed to mix with the people too much.
In a sense this is kind of the same thing. He wasn't
you know like the כהן גדול was supposed to be
distinguished.